<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A persvvassion to loyalty, or, The subject's dutie vvherein is proved that resisting or deposing of kings (under what spccious [sic] pretences soever couched) is utterly unlawfull / collected by D.O.</title>
            <title>Herod and Pilate reconciled</title>
            <author>Owen, David, d. 1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53652</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O704</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36621</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15746114</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15746114</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104600</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53652)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104600)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1153:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A persvvassion to loyalty, or, The subject's dutie vvherein is proved that resisting or deposing of kings (under what spccious [sic] pretences soever couched) is utterly unlawfull / collected by D.O.</title>
                  <title>Herod and Pilate reconciled</title>
                  <author>Owen, David, d. 1623.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reprint of the original manuscript entitled: The power of princes and the duty of subjects. Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bristol Public Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prerogative, Royal --  England.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104600:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Perſvvaſsion to Loyalty, OR THE SVBIECTS DVTIE.</p>
            <p>VVherein is proved that reſiſting or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of Kings (under what ſpecious preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſoever coached) is utterly unlawfull.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Collected by</hi> D. O.</p>
            <p>Dedicated to all dutifull Subjects.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed. 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:104600:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104600:2"/>
            <head>To the dutifull Subject.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Puritan-Church-Policie,</hi> and the <hi>Ieſuitical ſociety</hi> began together:<note n="a" place="margin">See M. <hi>Heokers</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face. And the preface of <hi>Che<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nic</hi> before his examen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Trent.</hi>
               </note> the one in <hi>Geneva,</hi> 1536. and the other in <hi>Rome,</hi> 1537. ſince their beginning, they have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtirred themſelves buſily (<hi>as he that compaſſeth the</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Iob. 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>Earth, or they that coaſted ſea and land</hi>) each one in his order. The <hi>Puritan</hi> to breake downe the wall of <hi>Sion,</hi> by diſturbing the peace of the <hi>Reformed Church:</hi> the <hi>Ieſuite</hi> to build up the ruines of <hi>Babilon,,</hi> by maintaining the abhomination of the <hi>deformed Synagogue.</hi> Theſe (though brethren in ſedition and heady) are <hi>head-ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 23.15.</note> the one ſtaring to the <hi>Presbytery,</hi> and the other to the <hi>Papacy,</hi> but they are ſo faſt linked behind, and <hi>tayle-tyed</hi> together with <hi>firebrands</hi> betweene them, that if they be not quenched by the power of Majeſty, they cannot choſe (when the meanes are fitted to their plot) but ſet the <hi>Church</hi> on fire, and the <hi>ſtate</hi> in an uprore. <hi>Their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and long prayers,</hi> their <hi>much vehement preaching,</hi> and ſtout oppoſition againſt <hi>orders eſtabliſhed,</hi> their ſhew of auſterity in their converſation, and of ſingular learning in their profeſſion, <hi>(as the evil fiend transformd into an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of light)</hi> brought them firſt to admiration Whereby they have not only <hi>robbed widowes houſes</hi> under pretence of prayer, &amp; ranſacked their <hi>ſeduced diſciples</hi> by ſhew of
<pb facs="tcp:104600:3"/>devotion, but alſo battered the <hi>courts of Princes,</hi> by ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating the <hi>Peers</hi> againſt <hi>Kings,</hi> and the <hi>people</hi> againſt the <hi>Peeres</hi> for pretended <hi>reformation.</hi> And wheras God hath inſeparably annexed to the <hi>Crown of earthly Majeſty, a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Eccleſiaſtical ſoveraignty</hi> for the protection of <hi>piety</hi> and an abſolute <hi>immunity</hi> from the juditiall <hi>ſentence,</hi> and Martiall <hi>violence,</hi> for the preſervation of <hi>policie:</hi> Theſe ſectaries bereave Kings of both theſe their <hi>Princely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives, exalting themſelves</hi> (as the ſonne of perdition) <hi>above all that is called God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Thel. 2.3, 4.</note> Leaſt they might ſeeme <hi>ſine ratione inſanire,</hi> to ſow the ſeeds of Sedition without ſhew of reaſon, <hi>Caedem faciunt Scripturarum</hi> (as the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes in <hi>Tertullians</hi> time were wont to do) <hi>in materiam ſuam,</hi> they kill the Scripture to ſerve their turnes: and pervert the holy Word of the <hi>eternall God,</hi> by ſtrange in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, and wicked application againſt the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> by whom it was penned; the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Church,</hi> to whom it was delivered; and the practice of all the <hi>Godly,</hi> (as well under the <hi>Law</hi> as the <hi>Goſpel</hi>) that did beleeve, underſtand, and obeyit; to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine their late, and lewd opinions. I have in my hand <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove forty ſeveral places of the old and new Teſtament,</hi> which both the brethren of the enraged oppoſite faction do indifferently quote, and ſeditiouſly apply, in defence of their dangerous oppoſition, and damnable error, againſt the <hi>Eccleſiaſticall ſupremacy,</hi> and the <hi>indeleble character of royal inunction.</hi> Vnto the which places, falſly expounded, perverted and applyed, I have added the interpretation, of the learned <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſince the time of <hi>Martin Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> who began to diſcover the nakedneſſe of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church,</hi> 1517. More eſpecially inſiſting in the<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>K.</hi> Henry <hi>8. K.</hi> Iames. The Cranmer. Io. Whitgiſt. Rich. Bancroſt. <hi>Archb. of</hi> Cant. Henry <hi>Earle of</hi> Northampton. Robert <hi>Earle of</hi> Salisbury.</note> moſt
<pb facs="tcp:104600:3"/>mighty Kings, the moſt reverend Prelats,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The L.</hi> Burleigh <hi>L. Treaſurer of</hi> England. <hi>The L.</hi> Elſmere. <hi>L. Chancelor of</hi> England. <hi>The L.</hi> Stafford <hi>The L</hi> Cooke. <hi>B.</hi> Jewell. <hi>B.</hi> Horne. <hi>B.</hi> Pilkington. <hi>B</hi> Elmere. <hi>B.</hi> Couper. <hi>B.</hi> Bilſon. <hi>B.</hi> Babington. <hi>B.</hi> Andrews. <hi>B</hi> Barſow. <hi>B</hi> Bridges. <hi>D.</hi> Ackworth. <hi>D.</hi> Saravia. <hi>D.</hi> Coſens. <hi>D</hi> Surcliffe. <hi>D.</hi> Prythergh. <hi>D.</hi> wilkes. <hi>D.</hi> Morton. <hi>D.</hi> Tocker. <hi>M:</hi> Bekinſaw. <hi>M.</hi> Foxe <hi>M.</hi> Nowell. <hi>M.</hi> Hooker, <hi>and many others.</hi>
               </note> honourable Lords, loyall Clergy and other worthy men, that have in the <hi>Church of England,</hi> learnedly defended the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cely right, againſt diſloyall and undutifull opponents: I proteſt in all ſincerity, that I have not detorted any thing, to make either the <hi>cauſe</hi> it ſelfe, or the <hi>favourers</hi> of it more <hi>odious,</hi> than their own words, (publiſhed with the general approbation of their ſeverall favorits) do truly infer and neceſſarily inforce. I hope the loyall Subject, and <hi>Godly</hi> affected, will accept in good part my endeavour, and induſtry, intended for the glory of <hi>God,</hi> the honor of the <hi>King,</hi> and the diſcovery of <hi>the ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</hi> The diſpleaſure of the <hi>Malecontented-factious</hi> (which can no more abide the truth, then the owles can light, or the frantique the Phyſitian) I neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard nor care for. <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:104600:4"/>
            <head>The Table of the Book.</head>
            <list>
               <item>The
<list>
                     <item>duty of
<list>
                           <item>Prelates,</item>
                           <item>Peeres,</item>
                           <item>People, by
<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Scripture,</hi> Chap. 1. Pag. 1.</item>
                                 <item>Fathers of the
<list>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>first</hi> 300 <hi>yeares,</hi> cap. 2 pag. 3</item>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>ſecond</hi> 300 <hi>yeares,</hi> cap. 3 pag. 6</item>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>third</hi> 300 <hi>yeares,</hi> cap. 4 pag. 14</item>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>fourth</hi> 300 <hi>yeares,</hi> cap. 5 pag. 16</item>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>fift</hi> 300 <hi>yeares,</hi> cap. 6 pag. 20</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sedition of
<list>
                           <item>Putitans</item>
                           <item>Papiſts
<list>
                                 <item>Concord in the matter, of ſedition. <hi>cap. 7. p. 24.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Diſcord in the manner, of ſedition. <hi>cap. 7. p. 24.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Danger of their doctrine to Prince. People, <hi>cap. 8. p. 26</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Puritan-Jeſuitiſme, or the generall conſent of the principall Puritans and Ieſuits, against Kings, from the yeare <hi>1536,</hi> untill the yeare <hi>1602,</hi> out of the moſt authentique Authors. <hi>cap 9. p. 27.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104600:4"/>
            <head>The firſt Chapter proveth by the teſt mony of Scripture, that Kings are not puniſhable by man, but reſerved to the Judgement of GOD.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>INGS have their Authority from God,<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 13.1</note> and are his Vicegerents in earth<note n="b" place="margin">Pro. 8.15.</note>, to execute juſtice and judgement for him amongſt the ſonnes of Men<note n="c" place="margin">2 Chron. 196.</note>. All Subjects (as well Prelates and Nobles, as the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour people) are forbidden with the <hi>tongue,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile Kings,<note n="d" place="margin">Exo. 22.28</note> with the <hi>heart,</hi> to thinke ill of them<note n="e" place="margin">Eccl 10.20</note>, or with the <hi>hand,</hi> to reſiſt them<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 13.2</note>. The great King of Heaven doth impart his owne Name unto his LIEUTENANTS the Kings of the Earth: and calleth them <hi>Gods,</hi> with an <hi>ego dixi</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 8 2.6</note>. Whoſe Word is <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Amen:</hi> with this only difference, that theſe <hi>Gods ſhall dye like men</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 82.7</note>, and fall like other Princes. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Nathan</hi> the man of God, muſt reprove <hi>David,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">2 Sam. 12.7.</note>, that he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and be ſaved. And the Sages, Iudges, and Nobles, (without feare or flattery) muſt adviſe and direct <hi>Roboam.</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">1 Reg. 12.7.</note> Other attempts againſt Kings, the King of Kings hath neither commanded in his Law, nor permitted in his Goſpel. <hi>David</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) <hi>null<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus tenebatur,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>David</hi> though he were an Adulterer,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apolog.</hi> David <hi>cap.</hi> 10.</note> and an Homicide, was tyed to no Law: for Kings are free from bonds, and can by no compulſion of Law, be drawn to puniſhment, being freed by the power of Government. Thus far <hi>Ambr.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saul</hi> the firſt King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was rather a monſter, than a man: after the ſpirit of God had forſaken him, &amp; the evil ſpirit was come upon him<note n="m" place="margin">1 Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.14.</note>. There were not many ſins againſt God, Man, or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, wherein he tranſgreſſed not; yet his exceſſe was puniſhed,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:104600:5"/>neither by the Sacerdotall Synod, nor the ſecular Senate: <hi>Who can loy his hand on the Lords Annointed, and be guiltleſſe</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">1 Sam. 16 9:</note>? The very An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointment was the cauſe of Sauls immunity from all humane coer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> affirmeth, <hi>Quaero ſi non habebat. Saul ſacramenti ſanctitatem,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> contr. lit. Petil l. <hi>2</hi> c. <hi>48.</hi>
                  </note> quid in eo David venerabatur?</hi> If <hi>Saul</hi> had not the holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Sacrament, I aske what it was that <hi>David</hi> reverenced in him; he honoured <hi>Saul</hi> for the ſacred and holy unction, while he lived: and revenged his death. Yea, he was troubled and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at the heart, becauſe he had cut off a lappe of <hi>Saules</hi> garment. Loe, <hi>Soul</hi> had no innocency, and yet he had holineſſe: not of life, but of unction. So far <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who queſtioned <hi>David</hi> for his murther and adultery? who cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured <hi>Salomon</hi> for his idolatry? though their c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nes were capitall by the Law of God. After that Kingdome was divided, all the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and moſt of the Kings of <hi>Iudah,</hi> were notorious I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters: yet during thoſe Kingdomes, which endured above 200 yeares, no Prieſt did challenge, no States-men did claime power from the higheſt, to puniſh or depoſe their Princes. And the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets perſwaded all men to obey, and endure thoſe idolatrous Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whoſe impiety they reproved with the loſſe of their lives,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſled when the people would have made him a King<note n="a" place="margin">Joh. 6.15</note>. He payed tribute for himſelfe and <hi>Peter</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 17.27.</note>. When the queſtion was propounded concerning the <hi>Emperours</hi> Subſidy, he concluded for <hi>Caeſar</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 22.21.</note>. And ſtanding to receive the judgement of death before <hi>Pilate,</hi> he acknowledged his power to be of God<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 19.15.</note>, This <hi>Saviour of Mankind,</hi> whoſe actions ſhould be our inſtruction, did never at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to change that Government, or to diſplace thoſe Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, which were directly repugnant to the ſcope of <hi>information</hi> that he aymed at.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> did indeed reprove King <hi>Herod</hi> with a <hi>Non licet</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Mar. 6 18</note>, but he taught not the Souldiers to leave his ſervice, or by ſtrife and impatience, to wind themſelvs out of the band of allegiance, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Law had left them, and the Goſpell found them<note n="f" place="margin">Luk. 3.14</note>.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle delivered unto the Church the Doctrine of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and patience, which they had learned by the Precept, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the practiſe of our Lord Chriſt. <hi>Peter</hi> commandeth obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to all manner of men in Authority<note n="g" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.15.</note>. <hi>Paul</hi> forbiddeth reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance againſt any power<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 13.1, 2, 3.4.</note>, And S. <hi>Iude</hi> maketh it blaſphemy, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile Government, or to ſpeake evill of Governours<note n="i" place="margin">Iude 8.</note>. <hi>If therefore an Angell from heaven preach otherwiſe, than they have delivered, let him be accurſed</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Gal. 1.8.</note>.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:104600:5"/>
            <head>The ſecond Chapter prooveth the ſame by the Fathers of the firſt <hi>300</hi> yeares.</head>
            <p>THe true Church, which had the Spirit of underſtanding, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the voyce of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> from the voyce of a <hi>ſtranger,</hi> never taught, never practiſed, never uſed or approoved other weapons, than ſalt teares, and humble prayers againſt the <hi>Paganiſme, Hereſie, Apoſtacy</hi> and <hi>Tyranny</hi> of earthly Kings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iuſtinus Martyr, Tertullian</hi> and <hi>Cyprian,</hi> ſhall beare witneſſe for 300 years, wherein the Kings and Potentates of the earth, bathed themſelves in the bloud of innocents, and proſeſſed enmity againſt Chriſt and his ſervants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ad inquiſitionem veſtram, Christianos nos eſſe profitemur,</hi> &amp;c. At your inquiſition we profeſſe our ſelvs to be Chriſtians, though we know death to be the guerdon of our profeſſion (ſaith <hi>Iustin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> to the Emperor <hi>Antonius</hi>) did we expect an earthly kingdom,<note place="margin">Second. apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. ad <hi>Ant.</hi> Imp. p. <hi>113.</hi>
               </note> we would deny our Religion, that eſcaping death, we might in time attain our expectation: But we feare not perſecution, which have not our hope fixed on the things of this life, becauſe we are certainly perſwaded that we muſt dye. As for the preſervation of publike peace, we Chriſtians yeeld to you (O Emperor) more help and aſſiſtance, than other men. For we teach, that no evill doer, no covetous man, nor ſeditious that lyeth in wait for bloud, can have acceſſe to God: And that every man doth paſſe to life or death, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the merit of his deeds. Thus far he.</p>
            <p>We (ſaith <hi>Tertullian</hi> to <hi>Scapula</hi> the Viceroy of <hi>Carthage</hi>) are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famed,<note place="margin">Tertull. <hi>lib. au</hi> Scap.</note> for ſeditious againſt the Imperiall Majeſty: Yet were the Chriſtians never found to be <hi>Albinians, Nigrians,</hi> or <hi>Caſſians (Albi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Niger, and Caſſius were traytors againſt Marcus Antonius, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modus, Pertinax and Severus the Emperors)</hi> but they that ſweare by the Emperors deity, the very day before; they that vowed &amp; offred ſacrifice for the Emperor's health, are found to be the Emperor's e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. A Chriſtian is enemy to no man, much leſſe to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror: knowing, that the Imperiall Majeſty, is ordained of God, and therefore neceſſarily to be loved, reverenced, and honored, whoſe proſperity, together with the welfare of all the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire they deſire ſo long as the world ſtandeth. We do therfore honour the Emperor, in ſuch ſort, as is lawfull for us, and expedient for him: we reverence him as a mortall man, next unto God, of whom he holdeth all his authority, only ſubject to God, and ſo we make him,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104600:6"/>ſoveraigne our all, in that, we make him ſubject, but to God alone: So far <hi>Tertullian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſheweth many good reaſons, for the patience of the Saints, in his book againſt <hi>Demetrianus.</hi> God (ſaih he) is the reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of his ſervants, when they are annoyed. Wherefore no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian when he is apprehended, doth reſiſt or revenge himſelf againſt your unjuſt violence, though the number of our people be very great. The confidence we have, that God will reward, doth confirm our patience, the guiltleſſe give way to the guilty, the innocent reſt content with their undeſerved puniſhment and tortures, being cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly aſſured that the wrong done to us, ſhall not be unrewarded. The more injury we ſuffer, the moſt juſt and grievous ſhall God's vengeance be on them that perſecute us. It is therfore cleare and manifeſt, that the plagues which comed own from Gods indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, do not come through us poore perſecured Chriſtians, but from him whom we ſerve, for the wrong done unto us. So far <hi>Cyprian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As many as lived according to Chriſt's inſtitution, did never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile the government of Tyrants, much leſſe by force reſiſt their vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, following the patience of Chriſt, who could by his own power, the might of his Angels, or the ſtrength of his creatures, have at the firſt withſtood, or at the laſt revenged, the injury of the people,<note place="margin">Ioh 19.15 Iohn 8.22 Luk. 23.11 Mar. 15 15 Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.27, 28, 29.</note> the buffet of the Prieſts ſervant, the ſcorn of <hi>Herod,</hi> the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Pilate,</hi> and the violence of the ſouldiers. He yeelded him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe patiently to death, to teach all his Diſciples, that an injury done by authority, is patiently to be endured, not forcibly to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled. As ſoon alſo as <hi>Paul</hi> became a Chriſtia, his ſeditious and bloudy ſpirit, which he had learned of the Phariſies, was changed into a deſire of peace and quietneſſe. He honored the heathen Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, as <hi>Agrippa, Foelix</hi> and <hi>Liſias,</hi> ratifying his doctrin, by the practiſe of his life. I know that Cardinall <hi>Alane,</hi> Cardinall <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, Ficlerus, Simancha,</hi> and other upholders of the Papall tyranny, that <hi>Stephanus Iunius, Franciſcus Hottomanus, Georgius Buchananus,</hi> and other pillars of the <hi>Puritan</hi> anarchy, do anſwer, that the Church then, as it were ſwathed in the bonds of weakneſſe, had not ſtrength ſufficient to make powerfull reſiſtance. But theſe <hi>Fathers</hi> that then lived, do convince them, and all other ſectaries of falſhood, by making demonſtration of the ſtrength and potency of the godly Chriſtians, in caſe they would have put their forces to the ſtrongeſt proofe. Seeing that all publike places, as Courts, Camps, Conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Cities, and countrey Villages, were ſtored and furniſhed with men of that profeſſion and quality, as doth moſt evidently appeare
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104600:6"/>by the words of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> in his Apologetical defence of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na nox pauculis faculis,</hi> &amp;c. One night with a few firebrand, would yeel us ſufficient revenge, if it were lawfull for us to requit evill for evill. But God forbid, that Chriſtians ſhould either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge themſelves with humane fire, or be grieved to ſuffer that wherewith they are tried. Were we diſpoſed, not to practiſe ſecret revenge, but to profeſſe open hoſtility, ſhould we want number of men, or force of Armes? Are the <hi>Moores,</hi> or the <hi>Parthians,</hi> or any one nation whatſoever, more in number than we, that are ſpread o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all the World? We are not of you, and yet we have filled all the places and rooms which you have. Your Cities, Iſlands, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, Towns, Aſſemblies, your Tents, Tribes, and Wards; yea, the Imperiall Pallace, Senate and ſeats of Iudgment. For what war, were not we able &amp; ready, though we were fewer in number than you, that go to our Martyrdom ſo willingly? If it were not more lawfull in our Religion to be ſlaine, than to ſlay? We could with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out armour, not by rebelling againſt you, but by departing from you, do you diſpleaſure enough, even with our ſeparation. For if ſo great a multitude, as we are ſhould break out from you, in any other corner of the world, the loſſe of ſo many citizens would ſhame and puniſh you. You would feare to ſee your ſelves left ſolitary, even amazed, as among the dead. You ſhould then ſee ſilence and deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion every where. You would have many more enemies than in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants. Whereas now, you have fewer enemies, becauſe of the multitude of your citizens that are almoſt all Chriſtians. <hi>Haec Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullianus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſee by theſe three witneſſes, that the Church of God, in the firſt 300 years wanted, neither number of men, ſtrength, nor cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to reſiſt perſecution, and to have eſtabliſhed the Chriſtian Faith, if that courſe had been lawfull: but becauſe their Lord had given them no ſword to ſtrike withall, they choſe rathe to be crowned Martyrs for their Religion, than to be puniſhed as tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors for rebellion. What number of men, what ſtrength of armes had the Church (thinke you) the next 300 years after it had been backed by Princes, defended by Laws, provoked by Honorable fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors to profeſſe Chriſtianity? Yet all that while the ſervants of God, neither did nor would reſiſt Apoſtaſie, Hereſie, or Tyranny: but yeelded their lives with all ſubmiſſion, though they wanted neither meanes nor multitude, convenient for any wars, as the next chapter by impregnable demoſtration ſhall ſhew.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:104600:7"/>
            <head>The third Chapter prooveth by the Fathers of the ſecond <hi>300,</hi> years, that the pleaſure of Princes must be endured with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, when their decrees cannot be obeyed with a good Conſcience.</head>
            <p>THe next 300 yeares, the Chriſtians did as patiently endure Hereſie, Apoſtaſie and Tyranny, to the glorious tryall of their Faith, and the eternall reward of their Patience. Whereof wee have a cloud of witneſſes, namely, <hi>Hoſius, Liberius, Athanaſius, Hilarius, Baſilius Magnus, Gregorius Nazianzenus, Lucifer Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritanus, Cyrillus Alexandrinus, Optatus Milevitanus, Ambroſius, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtinus, Chryſoſtomus, Leo</hi> the firſt, and <hi>Gregory</hi> the great.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hoſius</hi> was a famous Confeſſor in the Church, before <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, a worthy Biſhop during that Emperor's raigne, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his death greatly eſteemed of all good men, yea even of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> the <hi>Arrian</hi> Emperor himſelfe, for his old age, great experience, excellent learning, and good converſation. When this worthy Prelate, was commanded by the Emperour, to ſubſcribe to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> he returned to the Imperiall Majeſty, this ſtout, conſtant, Chriſtian and dutifull anſwer; <hi>Ego confeſſionis mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus imple vi primum, cum perſecutio moveretur, ab avo tuo Maximi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niano:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Obſequere &amp; ſcribe contra <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſium</hi> qui enim contra il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ſcribit ille planeono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſcum, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> I was then a confeſſor when your grandfather <hi>Maximinian</hi> perſecuted the Church. And if you do now raiſe perſecution, I am ready to endure any thing, rather then bettray the truth and ſhed innocent bloud. I do not like your manner of writing againſt <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius;</hi> Ceaſe from it, be not of the <hi>Arrian</hi> opinion; Give no eare to the Eaſtern Biſhops: beleeve me rather, that for age might be your grandfather. Leave off, I beſeech you, and call to mind, that you are a mortall man. Feare that dreadfull day of Iudgment. Enterpoſe not your ſelfe (O Emperor) into the Eccleſiaſticall ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, neither command us in this kind to condemne the innocent; but learn rather of us. God hath entruſteed your Majeſty with the Empire, and committed unto us the ſervice of the Church: he that with an envious eye maligneth your Imperiall Soveraignty, contradicteth the ordinance of God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſius a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Athan.</hi> ad ſolitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am vitam agentes.</note> Take heed (O Prince) leaſt drawing to your ſelfe the right of the Church, you become guilty of grievous tranſgreſſion, It is written, <hi>Give unto Caeſar the things that are Caeſars, and to God the things that appertaine to God:</hi> it
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104600:7"/>is therefore, neither lawfull for us Prieſts to uſurpe your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; nor for you Princes, to meddle with the ſacred ſervice and ſacrifices of the Church. Thus far <hi>Hoſius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee the grounds, that this good Biſhop ſtood upon: rather reſolved to ſuffer any death or torture, than by his conſent to betray the truth, or to condemne the guiltleſſe. He admoniſheth freely, and reprooveth ſharply, he offereth his life to the Prince's pleaſure: It was far from his meaning, to revile the ſacred Majeſty, or to ſtir up any rebellion againſt this Hereticall Emperor, which infringed the <hi>Canons</hi> of the Church, without all regard of truth or equity, to ſerve the humors of the <hi>Arrians,</hi> and to wrek his anger on them all, which yeelded not to that Hereſie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Liberius,</hi> a Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> did neither excommunicate nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe this wicked Emperour <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> but appeared at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and endured his pleaſure, to the admiration of the <hi>Arrians</hi> and the confirmation of the Chriſtians, as we find in <hi>Athanaſius, Trahitur Liberius ad Imperatorem,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Liberius</hi> was haled to the Emperor, when he came to his preſence, he ſpake freely, Ceaſe (ſaith he) O Emperor, to perſecute the Chriſtians, go not about by any meanes, to bring hereticall impiety into the Church of God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Liberius</hi> quo ſupra apud <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſ.</hi>
               </note> We are ready, rather to endure any torture, than to be called <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians.</hi> Compell us not to become enemies unto Chriſt. Fight not againſt him (we beſeech you) that hath beſtowed the Empire up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you. Render not impiety to him for his grace, perſecute them not which beleeve in him, leaſt you heare,<note place="margin">Acts 9.5,</note> 
               <hi>it is hard for thee to kicke againſt the pricke.</hi> Oh would to God you did ſo heare it, that you might (as <hi>Paul</hi> did) beleeve it. Loe we are at hand, and come to your preſence, before our enemies the <hi>Arrians</hi> can invent any thing to informe againſt us, we haſtened to come at your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, though we were aſſured of baniſhment: that we might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide our puniſhment, before any crime could be objected, much leſſe prooved againſt us. Whereby it may appeare, that all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are (as we now be) undeſervedly puniſhed, and the crimes laid to their charge not true, but fained by ſycophancy or deceitfull ſubtilty.</p>
            <p>Thus ſpake <hi>Liberius,</hi> and every man admired his reſolution; but the Emperour for anſwer commanded him to baniſhment. Thus far he.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Liberius</hi> had not learned the language of his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour <hi>Pius Quintus,</hi> when hee bellowed againſt our late Queene, nor that principle of the <hi>Puritans,</hi> that the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104600:8"/>officer may uſe force of armes againſt the chiefe Magiſtrate that ſhall become a tyrant <hi>(whereof every ſeditious ſectary will be judge)</hi> and not only defend himſelfe and his own people, but alſo any other that ſhall fly unto him.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Politia Christ.</hi> lib. 6 cap. 3.</note> Which opinion <hi>Lambertus Danaeus</hi> avouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, contraty to the Law, the Goſpel and the generall conſent of all Orthodoxall Fathers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hilarius,</hi> a Biſhop of <hi>France,</hi> wrote the ſame time to this ſame Emperor in moſt humble manner,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hilarius</hi> ad Imper. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</note> 
               <hi>Benefica natura tua domine beatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſime Auguſte:</hi> Your milde nature, moſt bleſſed Emperor, agreeing with your gracious diſpoſition, and the mercy which floweth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundantly from the fountain of your fatherly godlineſſe, do aſſure us, that we ſhall obtaine our deſire. We beſeech you, not only with words, but alſo with teares, that the Catholique Churches, be no longer oppreſſed with grievous injuries, and endure intollerable perſecutions, and contumelies, and that (which is moſt ſhamefull) even of our brethren. Let your Clemency provide, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Surely, if it had then been known that the <hi>Pope,</hi> by his abſolute power or indirect authority, could have puniſhed or depoſed Kings, which the Papiſts avouch, or for the Peeres or the People to have done it, which the <hi>Puritanes</hi> affirme, ſome of theſe old Biſhops would have preſſed that point againſt this hereticall Prince, which abuſed his ſword to the blaſpheming of Chriſt, the murthering of the Saints, the ſeducing of many thouſand ſoules: by ſtrenghtning, maintaining and eſtabliſhing the <hi>Arrian</hi> error. But they took it to be no Chriſtian mans part, to beare armour (no not defenſive) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Prince, though never ſo wicked, cruell or ungodly.</p>
            <p>Holy <hi>Athanaſius</hi> confeſſeth the power of Kings to bee of God, and their impiety not to be puniſhed by man. <hi>Sicut in toto mundo Deus Rex eſt Imperator &amp; poteſtatem exercet in omnibus:</hi> As God is King and Emperor over all the World,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad</hi> Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och. <hi>queſt.</hi> 55.</note> and exerciſeth his power in all creatures: ſo the King and Prince is over all earthly men, and doth by his abſolute power what he will, even as God himſelf. <hi>Haec ille.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When it was objected againſt this reverend Father <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> that he had incenſed <hi>Conſtans</hi> the religious Emperor of the Weſt, againſt <hi>Conſtantius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apolog.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than. <hi>ad</hi> Conſtant.</note> in the behalfe of the perſecuted Chriſtians: he cleared himſelf from that accuſation, in an Apology to the ſaid Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Conſtantius.</hi> The Lord, ſaith he, is my record, and his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed your brother, that I never made mention of your Majeſty for any evill before your brother of bleſſed memory, that religious Emperor <hi>Conſtans.</hi> I did never incite him againſt you, as theſe <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:104600:8"/>do ſlander me, but whenſoever I had acceſſe unto him, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted your gracious inclination. God knoweth what mention I made of your godly diſpoſition. Give me leave and pardon, moſt courteous Emperor, to ſpeake the truth. The ſervant of God <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans</hi> was not eaſily drawn to give eare to any man in this kind. I was never in ſuch credit with him, that I durſt ſpeake of any ſuch matter, or derogate from one brother before another, or talke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfully of one Emperor, in the hearing of another. I am not ſo madde, neither have I forgotten the voyce of God, which ſaith, <hi>Curſe not the King in thine heart, and backbite not the mighty in the ſecrets of thy chamber: for the birds of the ayre ſhall tell it, and the winged foule ſhall bewray thee.</hi> If then, the things that be ſpoken in ſecret againſt Princes cannot be hid: Is there any likelyhood, that I in the Emperor's preſence and before ſo many, as continually at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended his perſon, would ſay any thing otherwiſe then well of your Majeſty? Thus far <hi>Athanaſ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">L Cook in his ſpeach at <hi>Garnets</hi> arraigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>This is ſounder and ſeemelier doctrin for Subjects, than that which <hi>Henry Garnet</hi> and <hi>Robert Teſmond,</hi> taught ſome <hi>Romiſh</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Gentlemen of <hi>England,</hi> who imployed <hi>Thomas Winter</hi> into <hi>Spaine,</hi> in the month of <hi>December, Anno Dom.</hi> 1601, to make requeſt to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> King, in the behalfe and names of the <hi>Engliſh Pope-Catholiques,</hi> that he would ſend an army hither into <hi>England,</hi> for the advancement of their Catholique cauſe; and to promiſe, that the forces of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> here ſhould be ready to do him ſervice againſt the late <hi>Queen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſelfe ſame doctrin of ſedition was publiſhed in the yeare af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>viz. Anno Dom.</hi> 1602, by <hi>Guilielmus Bucanus,</hi> a man of no mean eſteeme among the <hi>Puritans,</hi> and that at the earneſt requeſt of <hi>Beza</hi> and <hi>Goulartius,</hi> the chiefeſt Miniſters of the Church of <hi>Geneva,</hi> (if the Author himſelfe belye them not) whoſe words are as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: <hi>Subditis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fit publica &amp; manifeſta jaeviti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, licet fieri ſupplices, implorare auxilia ab aliis, &amp; ſuſcipere eorum defenſionem aliis Regibus licet:</hi> Subjects when they endure publique and manifeſt wrong,<note place="margin">Loc. com. Theol. loco. 77. p. 845.</note> may lawfully become ſuppliants to foraign States, and crave their ayd againſt their Princes, and other Kings ought to take upon them their defence and protection. So far <hi>Bucan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Subjects muſt ſquare their ſubjection, according to the rule of Gods Word, not after the affection and fancies of men.<note n="a" place="margin">1 Sam. 22 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.</note> 
               <hi>Saul</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>Doeg</hi> to murther 85 Prieſts, to deſtroy their City, men, women and children with the edge of the ſword. Did <hi>David</hi> for whom they were ſlain, when he had <hi>Saul</hi> in his power, take re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104600:9"/> or ſuffer his ſervants to do it, when they were ready and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred themſelves to ſlay <hi>Saul? David</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">2 Sam. 11.4.17.</note> defiled <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rias</hi> his bed, and cauſed him to be killed: Did <hi>Abſolon</hi> well, to conſpire againſt him, that was both a murtherer and an adulterer? <hi>Salomon</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">2 Reg. 11.8.</note> brought into the land many ſtrange wives, and as many different Religions into the Church: Did the high Prieſt, the Peeres, the Prophets, or the people offer to chaſtice or depoſe him? <hi>Achab</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">1 Reg. 21 8, 9.</note> ſuffered <hi>Jeza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi> to put <hi>Naboth</hi> to death, and to kill the Lords Prophets: Did <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias</hi> depoſe him, intice his ſubjects to rebell againſt him, or implore foraigne aide to deſtroy him? <hi>Herod</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Marke 6.27. Act. 12.24.</note> beheaded <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> kill'd <hi>Iames,</hi> impriſoned <hi>Peter,</hi> and would have ſlain him alſo, if he had not been delivered by an Angell: Did <hi>Peter</hi> take vengeance on <hi>Herod,</hi> which he might have done with a word, as wel as on<note n="f" place="margin">Act: 5.5:</note> 
               <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias?</hi> No, he did leave him to the Lord, whoſe iudgment inſued in moſt<note n="g" place="margin">Acts 12.23.</note> fearefull manner. In a word, wicked Princes have never been lawfully puniſhed by Prelates, Potentates, or people of their Kingdome, as <hi>the Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Puritans</hi> aver; but muſt be reſerved to the judgement of God, as <hi>the Proteſtants</hi> affirme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gregory Nazianzen,</hi> in this Oration at the funerall of S. <hi>Baſil,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth, that the Emperor's Deputy in <hi>Pontus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baſilius magnus.</note> commanded S. <hi>Baſil</hi> to put out a widow, that had taken ſanctuary to ſave her ſelfe from forced marriage. The Biſhop (not willing to violate the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Laws granted by the Imperial Majeſty) refuſed ſo to do. The Governor call the Biſhop before him, threatned to whip him, and to teare his fleſh with iron books; the people hearing that indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity offered to the Biſhop, fell to an uprore, and would have ſlaine the Lieutenant,<note place="margin">Monodia Nazian, <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter opuſcula</hi> Baſil, <hi>fol:</hi> 95</note> 
               <hi>had not that innocent man of God, with much ado, ſtayd that furious tumult, &amp; delivered his perſecutor from that perill, to whoſe pleaſure he did afterward ſubmit himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> for his admirable learning called the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine,</hi> writeth of <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtata-Emperor's death: <hi>Iulian</hi> was puniſhed by the mercy of God, thorough the teares of Chriſtian men; which teare: were many, and ſhed of many, for that they had no other remedy, againſt that perſecutor. Thus far <hi>Nazianzen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This godly father lived under five Emperors, <hi>Conſtantius, Iuli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus, Valens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. cont. <hi>Iulian</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Valentianus</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> in all which time, he could finde no remedy againſt the Tyranny, Hereſy and Apoſtaſy of Princes, beſide prayers and teares: The Devill of Hell had not as yet hatched the diſtinctions of <hi>propriè</hi> and <hi>impropriè, directé</hi> and <hi>indirectè, ſimpliciter</hi> and <hi>ſecundum quid, abſolutè &amp; inordine ad ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualia,</hi> wherewith the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> do fill the ſchooles with clamorous
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104600:9"/>evaſions, the Church with erroneous ſuperſtition, and many Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſtates with tragicall ſedition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lucifer Calaritanus,</hi> in ſundry books againſt <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> uſeth many immodeſt and diſloyall ſpeeches: but he perſwaded not the Pope to depoſe him, the ſtate to puniſh him, the people to rebell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him or forraine aide to ſuppreſſe him; but threatened him with the dreadfull puniſhment of God. He that (in the ſervency of zeale) durſt call ſo cruell an Emperor, <hi>Theef, Church-robber, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer, Beaſt, Hangman, Heretique, Apoſtata, Idolator, the fore-runner of Antichriſt, and Antichrist himſelfe,</hi> would ſurely have encouraged the Pope, the Peeres, or the people, to have removed that evil King, and placed a better in his ſtead: If there had been any ſuch opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in thoſe daies, as our moderne <hi>Ieſuites</hi> and <hi>Puritans</hi> beare now the World in hand. As this Father in his writings kept not the modeſty of the other Fathers, which lived in that age under <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantius:</hi> ſo he did not continue in the unity of the Catholique Church.<note place="margin">Orat, in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit. ſratris Satir.</note> 
               <hi>Lucifer</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ambroſe) divided himſelf from our Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though he were baniſhed with us for our Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Ambroſe</hi> was commanded, to deliver up his Church in <hi>Millaine</hi> to <hi>Maxentius</hi> an <hi>Arrian</hi> Biſhop, he declared his reſolution in a ſermon to the people, which were very ſory for his departure.<note place="margin">Orat. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſii adpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulum inter epiſt. <hi>32.33.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quid turbamini? volens nunquam vos deſeram:</hi> Why are you trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled? I will never willingly depart from you. If I be compelled, I have no way to reſiſt: I can ſorrow, I can weep, I can ſigh, my teares are my weapons againſt Souldiers, Armour, Gothes: ſuch is the munition of a Prieſt; by any other meanes than teares, I nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought nor can reſiſt. So far <hi>Ambroſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not diſability but duty, not want of ſtrength and martial forces, but a reverend regard of the Emperors Majeſty, commanded by the Law of God, kept this bleſſed <hi>Ambroſe</hi> from reſiſting. For hé might eaſily have wrought the Churches liberty, his own ſafety, and the <hi>Arrians</hi> calamity, by the overthrow of the Emperour, through the force of the Gariſon in that City, which refuſed to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Prince to any other Church than that wherein <hi>Ambroſe</hi> was. The ſtout and peremptory anſwer of the Captaines and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, is thus reported by <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in an Epiſtle to <hi>Mercellina,</hi> a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious woman. <hi>Si prodire vellet haberet copiam ſe praeſto futuros:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 35.</note> The Emperor may go at his pleaſure, they would be ready to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend him, if he would go to the Catholique Aſſemblies, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, they would keep on their way to that Congregation wherin <hi>Ambroſe</hi> was. Thus far the <hi>Souldiers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:104600:10"/>
They refuſed (as you ſee) to obey, and preferred God's true Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, before the Emperor's favour: they reviled not his ſecred per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, they reſiſted not his Soveraign power, but yeelded themſelves to his mercy and pleaſure,<note place="margin">Epiſt eadem</note> to ſave their ſoules from Gods wrath and diſpleaſure, as we find in the ſame Epiſtle, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num Iob miraturus aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenderam,</hi> I went to Church to extoll the patience of <hi>Iob,</hi> where I found every one of my hearts, a <hi>Iacob,</hi> worthy to be extolled. In e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of you, <hi>Iob</hi> is revived; in each of you his patience, and vertue ſhined; what could be ſaid better by Chriſtian men, than that which the Holy Ghoſt this day ſpake in you? We beſeech (O Emperor) we offer not to fight, we feare not to dye, we intreat your clemency. Oh it was ſeemely for Chriſtian Souldiers, to deſire the tranquility of Peace and Faith, and to be conſtant in truth, even unto death. Thus far <hi>Ambroſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> relateth the ſame of the Chriſtian Souldiers, under <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtata Emperor: <hi>Iulianus extitit Imperator inſidelis,</hi> Iulian was an unbeleeving Emperor, was he not an Apoſtata? An Oppreſſor and an Idolater? Chriſtian Souldiers ſerved that unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving Emepror: When they came to the cauſe of Chriſt, they would acknowledge no Lord but him that was in Heaven: when they were commanded to adore Idoles, and to offer ſacrifice, they preferred God before their prince. But when he called upon them to war,<note place="margin">Auguſt: <hi>in</hi> Pſal. 124.</note> and bad them invade any Nation, they preſently obeyed. They did diſtinguiſh their eternall Lord, from the temporall King, yet they ſubmitted themſelves to their temporall Lord, for his ſake that was their eternall King.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deſchiſm. Donatiſt.</hi> Lib. 3.</note> So far he.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Optatus Milevitanus,</hi> is another pregnant witneſſe: <hi>Cum ſuper Imperatoren nemo ſit niſi ſolus Deus.</hi> Seeing there is no man above the Emperor, beſide God alone, which made the Emperor; <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> by advancing himſelfe above the Emperour, doth exceed the bounds of humanity, and maketh himſelf a God rather than man, in that he feareth and reverenceth him not,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Com. in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vang.</hi> Ioh l. 12. c. 36.</note> whom all men ſhould ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, next after God. So far <hi>Optat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>S. <hi>Cyril</hi> is of the ſame judgment. <hi>Cui legis prevaricatores liberare licet niſi Legis ipſius authori?</hi> Who can acquit them that break the Law, from tranſgreſſion, beſide the Law-giver? As we ſee by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, in all humane States, no man can without danger breake the Law, but Kings themſelves, in whom the crime of prevarica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath no place. For it was wiſely ſaid of one, that it is a wicked preſumption,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In Epist. ad</hi> Timoth. c. 2. v. 1.</note> to ſay to a King, <hi>Thou doeſt amiſſe.</hi> So far he.</p>
            <p>And alſo S. <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi> What meaneth the Apoſtle, ſaith he, to require Prayers &amp; Supplications, Interceſſions and Thankſgiving,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104600:10"/>to be made for all men? He requireth this to be done in the dayly ſervice of the Church, and the perpetuall rite of Dive Religion. For all the faithfull do know, in what manner prayers are powred out before the Lord morning and evening, for all the word: even for Kings, and every man in authority. Some man will (peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) ſay, that, <hi>for all,</hi> muſt be underſtood of all the faithfull. Which cannot be the Apoſtles meaning, as may appeare by the words fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, <hi>viz for Kings:</hi> ſeeing that Kings neither did then, nor in many ages after ſerve the living God, but continued obſtinatly in infidelity, which by courſe of ſucceſſion they had received. Thus far <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">See the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face before <hi>Baſilic. Dor.</hi>
               </note>Our Modern Reformers teach us that which <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> neither knew nor beleeved, that wicked Princes are not to be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, but to be reſiſted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the faction of <hi>Eutiches</hi> had prevailed againſt the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, <hi>Leo</hi> the firſt, had no other remedy than Prayers to God, ſighs, teares and petitions to the Emperor: <hi>Omnes partium noſtrarum Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae,</hi> &amp;c. All the Churches of theſe parts,<note place="margin">Bpiſt. <hi>24.</hi> ad <hi>Theod.</hi> Imper.</note> all we Prieſts even with ſighs and teares, beſeech your Majeſty, to command a generall Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>node to be held in <hi>Italy,</hi> that all offences beeing remooved, there may remaine, neither error in Faith, nor diviſion in L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e. Favor the Catholiques, grant liberty to protect the Faith againſt Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques, defend the ſtate of the Church from ruin, that Chriſt his right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand may ſupport your Empire. Thus far <hi>Leo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Gregory</hi> the great was accuſed for the murther of a Biſhop in priſon, he wrote to one <hi>Sabinianus,</hi> to cleare him to the Emperor and Empreſſe. <hi>Breviter ſuggeras ſereniſſimis Dominis meis:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epist.</hi> lib. 7. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 1.</note> You may briefly enforme my ſoveraigne Lord and Lady, that if I their ſervant, would have buſied my ſelf with the death of the <hi>Lombards,</hi> that Nation would by this time have had neither Kings, nor Duks, nor Earles, and ſhould have been in great confuſion and diviſion: but becauſe I ſtood in aw of God, I was ever afraid to meddle with the ſhedding of any mans bloud So far <hi>Gregory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Lombards</hi> were Pagans, invaders of the Countrey, ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſackers of the City, perſecutors of the Saints, robbers of the Church, oppreſſors of the poore: whom <hi>Gregory</hi> the firſt might, and would not deſtroy, <hi>quia Deum timuit,</hi> becauſe he ſeared God. It is very like, that his ſucceſſor <hi>Gregory</hi> the 7, feared neither God nor man, when he erected the papall croiſier againſt the regall ſcepter, and read the ſentence of deprivation againſt the Emperor <hi>Henry: Ego authoritate Apostolica,</hi> &amp;c. I by the power Apoſtolicall, do bereave
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104600:11"/>
               <hi>Henry</hi> of the <hi>German</hi> Kingdome, and do deprive him of all ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Chriſtian men, abſolving all men from the allegiance, which they have ſworne unto him. And that <hi>Rodolph,</hi> whom the Peeres of the Empire have elected, may govern the Kingdome: I grant all men, that ſhall ſerve him againſt the Emperor, forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their ſins,<note place="margin">Carol. Si<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gon. de Regoo It<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>l.</hi> 9. in vita <hi>Hen.</hi> 3.</note> in this life and in the life to come. As I have for his pride dejected <hi>Henry</hi> from the Royall dignity, ſo I do exalt <hi>Rodolph</hi> for his humility, to that place of Authority. Thus far <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the 7.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Benno</hi> Gard in vit. Greg <hi>7.</hi>
               </note>It is no wounder, that <hi>Gregory</hi> his chaire clave a ſunder, as ſome writers affirme, at the giving of this ſentence; becauſe the proud Pope, and his wicked ſentence, were too heavy a burthen for <hi>Peters</hi> ſtoole of humility to beare.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>The fourth Chapter proveth the Immunity of Kings by the Fathers of the third <hi>300</hi> yeares.</head>
            <p>AFter the death of <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, which was about the year of our Lord 604. <hi>Sabinianus</hi> did ſucceed him, who lived but one yeare, after whom came <hi>Boniface</hi> the 3, which obtained of <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas</hi> to be called <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall Biſhop;</hi> ſince that time <hi>periit virtus Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratorum &amp; pietas Pontificum,</hi> the Emperours waxed <hi>weake,</hi> and the <hi>Biſhops wicked.</hi> What the judgement of thoſe Fathers then was, concerning ſubjection to wicked Kings, I will make evident by the teſtimony of of <hi>Gregorius Turonenſis, Iſidorus, Damaſcenus, Beda, Fulgentius, Leo</hi> the 4, and the Fathers aſtembled in a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell at <hi>Toledo</hi> in <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gregory Turonenſis,</hi> acknowledgeth ſuch an abſolute power in <hi>Childerick</hi> a moſt wicked King of <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſtor. lib. <hi>5</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> as was free from all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troll of man. <hi>Si quis de nobis (Rex) juſtitiae limites tranſcendere vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luerit,</hi> &amp;c. If any one of us (O King) do paſſe the bonds of juſtice, you have power to correct him, but if you exceed your limit, who ſhall chaſtice you? We may ſpeake unto you; if you liſt not to hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, who can condemn you, but that great God, who hath pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced himſelf to be righteouſnes? <hi>Hactenus ille.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſidorus</hi> ſaith no leſſe for the immunity of the Kings of <hi>Spaine.</hi> Let all earthly Princes know, that they ſhall give account of the Church which Chriſt hath committed to their protection. Yea, whether the peace and diſcipline Eccleſiaſticall be advanced, by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104600:11"/>faithfull Kings, or diſſolved by the unfaithfull, he will require a reckoning at their hands, which hath left his Church in their power. So far <hi>Iſidor,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Damaſcene</hi> pleadeth not only for the Exemption of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Kings themſelves, but alſo of their Deputies.<note place="margin">Parall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 21.</note> The Governours (ſaith he) which Kings create, though they be wicked, though they be theeves, though they be unjuſt, or otherwiſe tainted with any crime muſt bee regarded. Wee may not contemne them, for their impiety: but muſt reverence them, becauſe of their authority, by whom they were appoynted our Governours. So farre he.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fulgentius</hi> ſaith, that no kind of Sedition can ſtand with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. <hi>Cum pro noſtra fide libere respondemus.</hi> &amp;c. When we anſwer freely for our profeſſion, we ought not to be taxed with the leaſt ſuſpition of diſobedience or contumely, ſeeing we are not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindfull of the Regall dignity, and do know, that we muſt feare God, and honour the King, according to the Doctrine of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, Give to each one his due, feare to whom feare,<note place="margin">Fulgent. <hi>ad</hi> Thraſim <hi>Reg.</hi> 1 Pet. 2.7.</note> honour to whom honour appertaineth. Of the which feare and honour Saint <hi>Peter</hi> hath delivered unto us the manifeſt knowledge, ſaying, As the ſervants of God, honour all men. love brotherly fellowſhip, feare God, honour the King. Thus farre <hi>Fulgent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Countriman <hi>Beaa,</hi> for his great learning called <hi>Venerable,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 4 <hi>expoſ. in</hi> Samuel. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sam. 24.6.</note> is of the ſame mind. <hi>David</hi> (ſaith he) for two cauſes ſpared <hi>Saul,</hi> who had perſecuted him moſt maliciouſly Firſt, for that he was his Lord, annoynted with holy oyle. And ſecondly, to inſtruct us by morall precepts, that wee ought not to ſtrike our governours, (though they unjuſtly oppreſſe us) with the ſword of our li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s: nor preſume ſlanderouſly, to teare the hemme of their ſuperfluous actions. So far he.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Leo</hi> the fourth about the yeare 846. agniſed all ſubjection to <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharius</hi> the Emperours:<note place="margin">Cap. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dist. 5.</note> I do profeſſe and promiſe (ſaith <hi>Leo</hi>) to obſerve and keepe unviolably, as much as lieth in me, for the time preſent and to come, your Imperial ordinances and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements: together with the decrees of your Biſhops, my prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors: It any man inform your Majeſty otherwiſe, know certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that he is a lyer. So far <hi>Leo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Biſhops of Spaine aſſembled in a Nationall Councell at <hi>Toledo,</hi> made this Decree againſt Perjury and Treaſon.<note place="margin">Concil. <hi>Tol.</hi> 5. Can. 2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ann. Dom. 636.</note> 
               <hi>Quicun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que amodo ex nobis:</hi> Whoſoever among us ſhall from this tune forward, violate the oath which he hath taken for the ſafegard
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104600:12"/>of this Countrey, the ſtate of the <hi>Gotiſh</hi> nation, and the preſervation of the Kings Majeſty: whoſoever ſhall attempt the Kings death, or depoſition: whoſoever ſhall by tyrannicall preſumption aſpire to the Regall Throne; let him be accurſed before the Holy Spirit, before the bleſſed Saints, let him be caſt out of the Catholike Church, which he hath polluted by perjury, let him have no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Chriſtian men, nor portion with the juſt, but let him be condemned with the Devill and his angels eternally, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his complices, that they may be tyed in the bond of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, which were joyned in the ſociety of ſedition. Thus far the Fathers in that Synod.</p>
            <p>I conclude therefore with theſe learned Fathers, that it is not for the people, otherwiſe then with humility and obedience, to control the actions of their Governors: but their duty is only to call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the God of Heaven, and ſo ſubmit themſelves to his mercy, by whoſe ordinance the Scepter is fallen into his hand and power, that enjoyeth the Crown, whether he be good or bad. A right of depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, muſt be either in him that hath an higher power, which is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God: or in him, that hath better right to the Crown, which the Pope cannot have, becauſe he is a ſtranger: nor the Peeres or people, becauſe they are ſubjects. Be the King for his Religion impious, for his Government unjuſt, for his Life licentious, the ſubject muſt endure him, the Biſhop muſt reprove him, the Councellor muſt adviſe him, all muſt pray for him, and no mortall man hath autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity to diſturbe or diſplace him, as may evidently be ſeene by the Chapter following.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>The fift Chapter confirmeth this Doctrine by the Fathers of the fourth <hi>300</hi> yeares.</head>
            <p>IN this age of the Church, the Popes exalted themſelves above all that is called God, and upon private diſpleaſures and quarrels, did curſe and ban Princes, incenſing their neighbour-Nations, and perſwading their own Subjects to make war againſt them, as if Chriſt had ordeined his Sacraments, not to be ſeales of Grace, and helps of our Faith, but hookes to catch Kingdoms, and rods to ſcourge ſuch Potentates as would not, or could not procure the Pope's favour. How far theſe Popiſh practiſes, did diſpleaſe the godly and learned, I will ſhew by S. <hi>Bernard, Waltramus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Nanumberg,</hi> the Epiſtle Apolegeticall of the Church of <hi>Leige</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104600:12"/>
               <hi>Paſchalis</hi> the Pope, and the Author of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth his Life.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Bernard,</hi> in one of his Sermons upon the words of <hi>Chriſt, I am the Vine,</hi> commendeth the anſwer of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine King, <hi>Bene quidam Rex, cum percuſſus humana ſagitta,</hi> &amp;c. It was well ſaid of a King when he was ſhot into the body with an arrow, and they that were about him, deſired him to be bound un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the arrow's head were cut out, for that the leaſt motion of his body would endanger his life; no, (quoth he) it doth not beſeem a King to be bound let the Kings power be ever ſafe and at liberty. And the ſame Father in an Epiſtle to <hi>Ludovicus Craſſus</hi> the King of <hi>France</hi> teacheth ſubjects, how to rebell and fight againſt their Princes; <hi>Quicquid vobis de Regno veſtro de anima &amp; Corona veſtra facere placuerit:</hi> Whatſoever you pleaſe to do with your Kingdom,<note place="margin">Bernard <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 221.</note> your ſoule, or your Crown, we that are the children of the Church cannot endure or diſſemble the injuries, contempt, and conculcati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our mother, Queſtionleſſe we will ſtand and fight even unto death in our mothers behalfe, and uſe ſuch weapons, as wee may lawfully, I meane not Swords and Speares, but Prayers and Teares to God.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Gregory</hi> the 7, had depoſed <hi>Henry</hi> the 4, he gave away the Empire to one <hi>Rodolphus</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> that was a ſworn ſubject to that diſtreſſed Emperor; which <hi>Rodolph,</hi> in a battaile againſt his Soveraigne Lord, loſt his right-hand, and gained a deadly wound. After his death, the Pope made one <hi>Hermanus</hi> King of <hi>Germany,</hi> who enjoyed his Kingdom but a little time, for he was ſlaine with a ſtone, which a woman threw upon him from a turret, as he made an aſſault (in ſport) againſt his own caſtle,<note place="margin">Ex vita <hi>Henr. 4.</hi> quae habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in faſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culorerum ſcien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>io um <hi>Col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ae impreſſo.</hi>
               </note> to try the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of his Souldiers. Then did <hi>Egbertus,</hi> by the Popes encourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſcend the Imperiall Throne, whereon he ſat but a while: for as he ſtepped aſide from his Army into a Mill, to reſt himſelf in the heat of the day, he was diſcovered by the Miller to the Emperor's friends, and loſt his life for his labour. During this hurly-burly in that State, <hi>Walthramus</hi> a godly Biſhop, wrote to one <hi>Ludovicus,</hi> an Earle of the Empire, diſwading him from partaking with the ſeditious againſt that good Emperor, whom the Pope had depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. <hi>Walthram</hi> by the grace of God, that he is, to <hi>Lewes</hi> the noble Prince, with inſtance of prayer, offreth himſelfe in all things ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable. Concord is profitable to every Realme, and Iuſtice much to be deſired: theſe vertues are the mother of devotion, and the conſecration of all honeſty. But whoſoever ſeeketh after civill diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104600:13"/>and incenſeth other to the effuſion of bloud, he is a murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer and partaketh with him, who gaping for bloud, goeth about ſeeking whom he may devoure: The worthy veſſell of election, that was taken up to the third Heaven, proteſteth, ſaying, Let e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſoule ſubmit himſelfe to the higher power, there is no power but from God. He that reſiſteth power, reſiſteth the ordinance of God. If that be true (which ſome men prate among women and the vulgar ſort) that we ought not to be ſubdued to the Kingly power, Then it is falſe which the Apoſtle teacheth, that every ſoule muſt ſubmit himſelfe under power and ſuperiority. Can the truth lye?<note place="margin">Epiſt. Wald. quae habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendice Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian. Scot.</note> Did not Chriſt the Lord ſpeake by the Apoſtle? Why do we provoke the Lord? Are we ſtronger than he? Doth not he thinke himſelfe ſtronger than the Lord, the reſiſteth the ordinance of God? Seeing there is no power but of God: What ſaith the Prophet? Confounded be they that ſtrive againſt the Lord, and they that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt him ſhall periſh. <hi>Rodolphus, Hermanus, Egbertus,</hi> with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Princes, reſiſted the ordinance of God, in <hi>Henry</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, but loe they are confounded, as though they had never beene, for as their end was ill, their beginning could not be good, <hi>&amp;c. Haec ille.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Paſchalis</hi> ſeeing the bad ſucceſſe of thoſe ſeditious ſubjects, which his predeceſſors <hi>Gregory</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbanus</hi> had armed againſt <hi>Henry,</hi> that worthy Emperor: did perſwade the Emperor's own ſon, againſt all Law of God, Nature and Nations, to rebell againſt his father. The Biſhop of <hi>Leige</hi> tooke the Emperors part, againſt this young Prince, for the which he was excommunicate, his Church interdicted, and <hi>Robert</hi> Earle of <hi>Flaunders</hi> commanded by the Pope, as he hoped to have the forgiveneſſe of his ſins, and the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to deſtroy that Biſhop and his falſe Prieſts.</p>
            <p>The Churchmen of <hi>Leige</hi> terrified with the Popes excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and fearing the Earles oppreſſion, wrote an Apology for themſelvs about the yeare 1106.<note place="margin">Epiſt. Leodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſium apud Simonem Scard.</note> We are excommunicate (ſay they) becauſe we obey our Biſhop, who hath taken part with his Lord the Emperor. Theſe are the beginnings of ſorrow; for Satan bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing looſed, compaſſeth the earth, and hath made a diviſion between the Prince and the Prieſt: who can juſtly blame the Biſhop that taketh his Lords part, to whom he hath ſworn allegiance? Perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is a great ſin, whereof they cannot be ignorant, that by new ſchiſme and novell traditions do promiſe to abſolve ſubjects from the guilt of perjury, that forſweare themſelves to their Lord the King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:104600:13"/>
In the progreſſe of their Apology they determine three great queſtions.</p>
            <p>Firſt, whether the Pope hath power to excommunicate Kings?</p>
            <p>Secondly, to whom it belongeth to inflict temporall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when Church-men offended againſt Faith, unity or good manners?</p>
            <p>And thirdly, what remedy ſubjects have againſt their Kings, that are impious or tyrannous? <hi>Si quis reſpectu ſancti Spiritus,</hi> &amp;c. If any man having reſpect to the Spirit of God, ſhall turn over the old and new Teſtament, he ſhall plainly find that Kings, ought not at all or very hardly be excommunicate, whether we conſider the etimology of their names, or the nature of their excommunication. Even til this day hath this point been queſtioned, and never deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined Kings may be admoniſhed and reproved, by ſuch as be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet and ſober men, for Chriſt the King of Kings in earth, who hath placed them in his own ſtead, hath reſerved them to his own judgement, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their anſwer to the ſecond queſtion, is grounded on the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> the practiſe of Princes, and the authority of <hi>Paul,</hi> Kings (ſay they) and Emperors by their publique Lawes, have forbidden heretiques, to enjoy any wordly poſſeſſion. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing we are no heretiques, and that it belongeth not to the Pope, but to Kings and Emperors to puniſh hereſies, why doth our Lord <hi>Paſchalis</hi> ſend <hi>Robert,</hi> his armour-bearer, to deſtroy the poſſeſſions and to overthrow the villages of the Churches, which in caſe they deſerved deſtruction, ought to be deſtroyed by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict of Kings and Emperors, which cary the ſword, not without good cauſe? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For anſwer to the third queſtion, they ſhew by ſundry places of Scripture, that there is no other helpe againſt evill Princes, than prayer and patience. <hi>Nihil modo pro Imperatore noſtro dicimus,</hi> &amp;c. We will for the preſent ſay nothing in defence of our Emperor, but this we ſay, though he were as bad as you report him to be wee would endure his government, becauſe our ſins have deſerved ſuch a Governor. Even ſuch a Prince ought not to be reſiſted by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, but endured by patience and prayer. <hi>Moſes</hi> brought many plagues upon <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> whoſe heart God had hardened, but it was by prayer and the lifting up his hands to heaven. And S. <hi>Paul</hi> requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth prayers to be made for all men, for Kings and ſuch as are in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority: which Kings were neither Catholikes nor Chriſtians. <hi>Baruch</hi> alſo from the mouth of the Prophet <hi>Jeremy,</hi> wrote unto the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:104600:14"/>Iews, which were captives unto the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that they muſt pray for the life of <hi>Nabuchadnezzar</hi> the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and <hi>Balthazar</hi> his ſon, that their dayes in earth may be as the dayes of Heaven,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> Leod.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth why we ought to pray for evill Kings namely, that under them we may lead a quiet life. It would becom an Apoſtolike man, to follow the Apoſtles doctrin: it were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall to follow the Prophet, <hi>&amp;c. Thus far they in their Epiſtle Apologeticall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He that wrote the life of this Emperor <hi>Henry</hi> the 4,<note place="margin">Vita <hi>Hen. 4</hi> quo ſupra.</note> an auncient, a modeſt, and an impartiall relator of ſuch occurrents as happened in his time, declareth his diſlike of the Popes practiſes, and the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines</hi> tumults againſt their ſaid Soveraigne Lord. <hi>Magnum mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do documentum datum eſt.</hi> A great inſtruction was given to the World, that no man ſhould riſe againſt his maſter. For the hand of <hi>Rodolph</hi> being cut off ſhewed a moſt juſt puniſhment of perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; he feared not to violate his fidelity ſworn to the King, and his right hand was puniſhed, as if other wounds had not beene ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to bring him to his death, that by the plague of the rebellious, the fault of rebellion might be perceived. Thus far he.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>The ſixth Chapter proveth the ſame by the testimony of the Writers from the <hi>1200</hi> yeares downward.</head>
            <p>I Will for concluſion produce <hi>Otho Friſingenſis, Thomas Aquinas, Gratianus, Philip the faire</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> in the time of <hi>Edward</hi> the 1, <hi>Vincentius</hi> and <hi>Aeneas Silvius,</hi> that afterward was Pope, by the name of <hi>Pius Secundus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Otho Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin in his Epiſtle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatory before his Chronicle.</note> 
               <hi>Otho Friſin genſis</hi> hath an excellent ſaying in his Epiſtle dedicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to <hi>Frederick Barbaroſſa, Cum nulla perſona mundialis inveniatur quae mundi Legibus non ſubjaceat,</hi> &amp;c. Although no earthly man can be found, that is not ſubject to the Laws of the World, and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of ſubjection, liable to correction: Kings as it were placed over Laws, are not reſtrained by them, but reſerved to the exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of God, according to the words of the King and Prophet, <hi>Against thee only have I ſinned.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.5.</note> It becommeth therfore a King, both in reſpect of the noble diſpoſition of his mind, and the ſpirituall il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumination of his ſoule, to have God, the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, ever in his mind, and by all meanes poſſible to take heed, that he fals not into the hands of God, ſeeing it is (as the Apoſtle ſaith) a fearefull thing to fall into the hands of the living God. It is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:104600:14"/>more fearefull for Kings, than for any other; becauſe Kings have none but God himſelfe above them, whom they need feare. It ſhall be ſo much more horrible for them, by how much they may offend more freely than other men. So far <hi>Otho.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aquin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>de regimine prin.</hi> lib. 1. cap. 6.</note> (if the tractate <hi>de Regimine Principum</hi> be his) maketh three ſorts of Kings; Kings by <hi>Election,</hi> Kings by <hi>Subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination,</hi> and Kings by <hi>Succeſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt, he ſaith, that they which did eſtabliſh, may aboliſh.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond, we muſt have our recourſe to him that did ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate the ſubordinate King: as the Iews did to <hi>Caeſar</hi> againſt <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod:</hi> for the laſt, his reſolution is, <hi>Recurrendum eſſe ad omnium Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem Deum,</hi> that we muſt fly to God, the King of all Kings, in whoſe only power it is to molifie the cruell heart of a Tyrant. And that men may obtaine this at the hands of God, they muſt ceaſe from ſin; for wicked Princes, by Divine permiſſion are exalted to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the ſins of the people, <hi>tollenda eſt igitur culpa ut ceſſat tyranno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum plaga,</hi> we muſt therefore remove our ſins, that God may take away his puniſhment. Thus far <hi>Thomas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gratianus,</hi> which compiled the Decrees, is very peremptory, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> ought not to medle with the temporall ſword, the ſtate of Common-wealths, or the change of Princes. He ſaith nothing indeed <hi>de Regni ordinibus,</hi> which in his time, and a 100 yeares after him, never dreamed of any ſuch authority. <hi>Cum Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus qui primus Apoſtolorum à Domino fuerat electus, materianlem<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium exerceret:</hi> When <hi>Peter</hi> whom the Lord had firſt choſen of all the Apoſtles, drew the material ſword, to defend his Maſter fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the injuries of the Iews, he was commanded to ſhearh his ſword:<note place="margin">Mat. 26.52</note> 
               <hi>For all that take the ſword, ſhall periſh by the ſword.</hi> As if Chriſt ſhould have ſaid, Hitherto it was lawfull for thee and thine aunceſtors to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute Gods enemies with the temporall ſword, hereafter thou muſt put up that ſword into his place, and draw the ſword of the Spirit, which is the Word of God, to ſlay the old man:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cauſ.</hi> 23. <hi>queſt.</hi> 8. <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ag.</hi> 1. Rom. 13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4.</note> whoſoever beſide the Prince, and without his authority, that hath lawfull power, and as the Apoſtle teacheth, <hi>beareth not the ſword in vaine,</hi> to whom every ſoule muſt be ſubject, whoſoever (I ſay) without or beſide the Princes authority, beareth the ſword, ſhall periſh by the ſword. Thus far <hi>Gratian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About the yeare 1300 began a quarrell between <hi>Boniface</hi> 8, and <hi>Philipus Pulcher</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King, about the collation of Benefices, Prebends and other Eccleſiaſticall promotions. Whereupon the Pope wrote unto the ſaid King, as ſolloweth: <hi>Boniface</hi> Biſhop
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:104600:15"/>the ſervant of Gods Servants, to his well-beloved Son <hi>Philip,</hi> by Gods grace King of <hi>France,</hi> greeting and bleſſing Apoſtolicall. Feare God and keepe his Law: We give thee to underſtand that thou art ſubject to us both in Spirituall things, and Temporall, and that no gift of benefices or prebends belongeth to thee. If thou have in thy hand any vacant, keep the profits of them to the Succeſſors and if thou haſt beſtowed any, we decree the collation voide, and recall it, how far ſoever it hath proceeded. Whoſoever beleeveth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, we account him a foole: Dated at <hi>Lateran</hi> the fourth of the Calends of <hi>December,</hi> and in the 6. yeare of our Papacy. King <hi>Philip</hi> returned his hautineſſe, a correſpondent anſwer, <hi>viz. Philip</hi> by the grace of God, King of <hi>France,</hi> to <hi>Boniface</hi> bearing himſelfe for Pope,<note place="margin">Philip. Pulcher.</note> 
               <hi>Salutem modicam ſive nullam Sciat tua maxima fatuitas.</hi> Lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle health or none at all. Let thy great fooleſhip know, that in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall things we are ſubject to no man. And that the gifts of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bends and Eccleſiaſticall promotions, made and to be made by us, were and ſhall be Lawfull, both in time paſt and in time to come. For ſuch collations belong to us in the right of our Crown: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, we will manfully defend the poſſeſſours of the ſaid dignities, and do judge them that thinke otherwiſe fooles and mad men. Given at <hi>Paris</hi> the Wedneſday after <hi>Candlemaſse,</hi> 1301. Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſſe this King that did ſo ſcornefully reject the Popes chalenge pretended from Chriſt, would little regard the claime of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, derived but from the people.</p>
            <p>The ſame buſie <hi>Boniface,</hi> of whom ſome write, that he came in like a <hi>Foxe</hi> craftely, raigned like a <hi>Lion</hi> cruelly, and dyed like a <hi>Dog</hi> miſerably, would take upon him the deciſion of a controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie between the Kings of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and commanded King <hi>Edward</hi> of <hi>England</hi> either to ceaſe his claime, or to ſend his procurators to the Apoſtolike ſea, to ſhew his right, and to receive ſuch order from the Pope, as juſtice and equity would require. The Lords and Commons then aſſembled in Parliament at <hi>Lincolne,</hi> ſent <hi>Boniface</hi> this anſwer in the Kings behalfe. Whereas our moſt dread Lord <hi>Edward</hi> by the grace of God, the Noble King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> cauſed your Letters to be read openly before us, touching cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine occurrents of ſtate between him and the King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> we did not a little marvaile at the contents thereof, ſo ſtrange and wonderfull, as the like hath never been heard of. We know (moſt holy father) and it is well known in this Realme, and alſo to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nations, that the King of <hi>England</hi> ought not to make anſwer for his right before any judge Eccleſiaſticall or ſecular: by reaſon
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:104600:15"/>of the free eſtate of his Royall dignity and cuſtome,<note place="margin">Parliament at <hi>Lincolne</hi> quoted by M. <hi>Beken-ſhaw.</hi>
               </note> without breach at all times unviolably obſerved: Wherefore after treaty had and diligent deliberation, this was our reſolution, that our ſaid King ought not to anſwer in judgement, nor ſend procura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors or meſſengers to your court: ſeeing that tendeth manifeſtly to the diſinheriting of the right of the Crown, the overthrow of the ſtate of the Kingdome, and the breach of the Liberties, Cuſtomes, and Lawes of our Fathers, for the keeping whereof, we are bound by the duty of an oath, and will (by Gods help) maintaine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend with all our power and ſtrength, &amp;c. Dated at <hi>Lincolne Ann. Dom</hi> 1301. <hi>&amp; anno, Edwardi primi</hi> 29. This was then the reſolution of the ſtate of this land: if our late ſectaries <hi>Popiſh</hi> or <hi>Puritan,</hi> bring in any other Doctrine, we may not leave the cawſey of truth and obedience, whereon our forefathers walked to their commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to follow theſe new guides, in their by-paths of pride, diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and contempt of authority, to our deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vincentius</hi> in his <hi>Speculo Hiſtoriali</hi> hath a notable place to diſſw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ade from ſedition and perjury. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t pace omnium bonorum dixerim,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>li.</hi> 15. <hi>c.</hi> 84.</note> 
               <hi>haec ſola novitas (ne dicam haereſis) nec dum è mundum emerſerat.</hi> That I may ſpeake with the favour of all good men, this meere novelty (if not hereſie) was not ſprung up in the world, that Preiſts ſhould teach Subjects, that they owe no ſubjection to wicked Kings, and albeit they have given an oath of fidelity unto them, they are not bound to keep it: Nay they that obey an evill Prince, are to be held as excommunicated, and all ſuch as rebell againſt him, are free from the guilt of the crime of perjury. So far he.</p>
            <p>I will end this Chapter with <hi>Aeneas Silvius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pius 2.</hi> de o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tu &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thor, imperii cap. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> who dyed in the yeare 1464 <hi>Sit tandem finis litium,</hi> Let there be an end of contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and one principall head to determine all Temporall matters: let the occaſion of perpetuall debate be taken away, let men ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg themſelvs ſubject to their Prince, and give reverence to him, whom God hath made his vicegerent on earth. As that which God commandeth muſt be obeyed without contradiction, ſo the Temporall Commandements of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> may not be reſiſted. But let the Kings themſelvs beware that they opreiſe no man unjuſtly, nor give their people cauſe to cry to God againſt them, for the earth is the Lords and the fulneſſe thereof: he will not forget the cry of the poore: and for the ſin of the Prince he tranſlateth the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from one Nation to another. There is nothing more offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to the greateſt God the King and Creator of Heaven and Earth, then the neglect of juſtice, and the oppreſſion of the poore:
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:104600:16"/>as the Pſalmiſt ſaith, <hi>The poore ſhall not alway be forgotten, and the patient abiding of the needy ſhall not periſh for ever.</hi> So far <hi>Silvius.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>The Seventh Chapter ſheweth the concord of Papiſt and Puritan for the depoſition of Kings, and their diſcord about the meanes and perſons to be imployed in the execution of their Deſignements.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>CHilderick</hi> was depoſed, and <hi>Pipine</hi> crowned King of <hi>France</hi> about the yeare 750. The truth of which Hiſtory is this: <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick</hi> voyd of all Princely gravity, gave himſelfe over to pleaſure and wantonneſſe, leaving the burthen of the State to <hi>Pipinus,</hi> that was his Lord <hi>Marſhall:</hi> Who conſpired with the Nobles, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance himſelfe, by the deſition of the King his maſter. To ſet a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter colour on the matter, <hi>Pipine</hi> ſent his Chaplaine to Pope <hi>Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> to have his anſwer to this Queſtion: <hi>Whether ſhould be King, he that bare the name and did nothing, or he he that grverned the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome?</hi> The Pope gave ſentence with the Marſhall againſt the King, whereupon, <hi>Childerick</hi> was made a ſhorne Monke, and <hi>Pipine</hi> a crowned King.</p>
            <p>It is a wonder to ſee how theſe oppoſite ſectaries, do inſiſt upon this fact of the <hi>French</hi>-men, to juſtifie their dangerous Doctrine, and ſeditious conſpiracies againſt Princes. As Card. <hi>Bellarmine de pontif. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 17. <hi>Thomas Harding</hi> againſt the <hi>Apologie</hi> of the Church of ENGLAND <hi>fol.</hi> 181. Franc. <hi>Fevardentius</hi> in his Commentary on <hi>Heſter</hi> page 85. <hi>Boucher, alias Raynolds de ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta abdicatione Henrici.</hi> 3 <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. <hi>Ficklerus de jure magiſtratuum fol.</hi> 30. <hi>Alexander Carerius patavinus de poteſtate Papae, lib.</hi> 2 <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>D. Marta de temporali &amp; ſpirituali pontificis poteſtate, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 23. and <hi>Doleman in his conference touching ſucceſſion parte.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>page</hi> 48. And alſo theſe <hi>Puritans, Chriſtopher Goodman in his treatiſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, pag.</hi> 53. <hi>George Buchanan de jure Regni apud Scotos, pag.</hi> 47. <hi>Danaeus de politia Chriſtiana lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>pag.</hi> 221, <hi>Brutus Celta de jure magiſtratuum pag.</hi> 286. <hi>Philadelphus dialogo</hi> 2, <hi>pag.</hi> 65. <hi>Franc. Hottomanus</hi> in his <hi>Francogallia cap.</hi> 12. and <hi>Speculum tyrannidis Philipi Regis pag.</hi> 27.</p>
            <p>Cardinall <hi>'Pellarmine</hi> the grand-maſter of Controverſies,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ontiſ.</hi> lib. 2. c. 17.</note> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure to heare that this depoſition was done by any other then the papall Authority.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caeterum quod monachus iſte</hi> (ſaith <hi>Lambertus Danaus</hi>) whereas
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104600:16"/>this monke <hi>Bellarmine</hi> contendeth that <hi>Childerick</hi> was lawfully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by Pope <hi>Zacharias,</hi> a ſtranger, a Prieſt, no Magiſtrate, but (in this reſpect) a private perſon, though he were Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naei <hi>ad</hi> Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 17 <hi>pag.</hi> 316.</note> Will he ever be able to prove or defend his aſſertion? Can <hi>Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> have authority in <hi>France,</hi> being a ſtranger? Can he depoſe the publike Magiſtrate, being but a private perſon? or transferre that principality to <hi>Pipin</hi> that he hath no right unto? and commit ſo many ſacriledges and impieties, ſtealing from <hi>Childerick,</hi> and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to <hi>Pipin</hi> another mans right? authoriſing ſubjects to violate their oaths, which they had ſworn to their King? tranſporting Kingdomes from one man to another, wheras it doth only belong to God to depoſe Kings, and diſpoſe of Kingdoms? Thou maiſt ſee <hi>(Bellarmin)</hi> how many outrages this thy <hi>Zachary</hi> hath committed, beſide that he did thruſt his ſickle into another mans harveſt, and meddled with the Cobler beyond his Laſt, in that, being but a Prieſt, he took upon him the deciſion of the right of Kingdomes. Thus far <hi>Danaeus,</hi> who is not ſo violent againſt the Pope,<note place="margin">Danaeus <hi>pol. Chriſt.</hi> l. 6 c. 3 <hi>pag.</hi> 414.</note> as he is virulent for the depoſing power of Peeres, or States of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>Men cannot ſay (as it is in the Proverb) <hi>nimium altercando ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas amittitur,</hi> ſeeing that in this oppoſition, the truth is not loſt, but divided among them. For their premiſſes, brought together, will unavoidably conclude, that this depoſing power, is neither in the Pope, the Peeres, nor the People. Though it were, the reaſon of the ſeditious <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Puritans, à facto, adjus,</hi> is ſophiſticall in the Schooles, where nothing can be concluded <hi>ex meris particulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> of meere particular inſtances. Abſurd in Law, <hi>quia legibus non exemplis vivitur,</hi> for men muſt do as the Law requireth, not as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men practiſe. Erroneous in Divinity, <hi>non ideo quia factum cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt.</hi> ad <hi>Conſen.</hi> de mendac. c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>faciendum credamus, ne violemus praeceptum dum ſectamur ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplum:</hi> We may not do that, which hath been done by other men, leaſt we break the Law of God, in following the example of man. And dangerous in policy, as my Lord of <hi>Northampton,</hi> the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of learning obſerveth. <q>The fly (ſaith that noble Earle) ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on the cart-whele, might as well wonder at the duſt raiſed in the way, as <hi>Gregory</hi> or <hi>Zachary,</hi> draw counſell to power, and make that fact their own which was hammered in the forge of ambition, contenanced with the colour of neceſſity, and executed by <hi>Pepin,</hi> a miniſter, that being weary of ſubordination, reſolved by this trick, when the meanes were fitted and prepared to the plot, to make himſelfe abſolute.</q> The caſe of Kings were pitifull,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:104600:17"/>if <hi>ex factis ſingularibus,</hi> it were lawfull to draw leaden rules in their diſgrace. Thus fas the Earle.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>The eight Chapter ſheweth the danger of this Doctrine, and the Originall of the Puritan poſition, concerning the power of ſtateſmen to puniſh and depoſe Princes in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies.</head>
            <p>THeſe deſperate attempts, ſuggeſted by the Devill, executed by the people, encouraged by the State, and approved by the Pope, muſt ſerve as admonitions to Princes, to humble themſelves before God: <hi>Qui non dabit Sanctos ſuos in captionem dentibus corum,</hi> who will not give his Saints for a pray to their teeth. For it is not heard (as our great King remembreth) <hi>That any Prince forgeteth himſelfe in his duty to God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Law of Monarch. pag. 60.</note> 
               <hi>or in his vocation? But God with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the plague revengeth the greatneſſe of his ingratitude.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe practiſes therefore muſt be no preſident for Peers or Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to follow, becauſe God hath forbidden Chriſtian ſubjects to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, though Kings raigne as Tyrants: and commanded them to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure with patience, though they ſuffer as Innocents. And alſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that in ſtead of releeving the Commonwealth out of diſtreſſe, which is ever the pretence of ſeditions practitioners, they ſhall heape miſchief on it, and deſolation on themſelves: as <hi>(Aquinas)</hi> if he be the Author of the book <hi>de regim. principum,</hi> ſheweth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly. <hi>Eſſet multitudini periculoſum &amp; ejus rectoribus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">de reg. prin. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> It were dangerous to ſubjects and governors, that any ſhould attempt to take away the life of Princes, though they were Tyrants: for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly, not the well diſpoſed, but the ill affected men, do thruſt themſelves into that danger. And the government of good Kings, is as odious to bad men, as the rule of Tyrants to good people. Wherefore the Kingdome, by this preſumption would be rather in danger to forgo a good Prince, than a wicked Tyrant. So far <hi>Thomas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They that are the authors or abettors of ſedition, can neither a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyd ſhame in Earth, nor eſcape eternall damnation. Though God the great Iudge do ſometime permit Rebels, in his Iuſtice to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile againſt Kings for their contempt of the Law of the higheſt, and the neglect of their own duty; The reward of Rebellion ſhall be no better than the recompence of Satan, who is the inſtrument of the Lords wrath for the puniſhment of all diſobedience. It is
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:104600:17"/>moſt true that as ſick men, neer their death, have many idle fancies,<note place="margin">Chryſoſſ.</note> ſo the World before the end thereof ſhall bee troubled with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny errours. In theſe declining dayes of the World, many Countreys, Cities and Cantons, renounced their old government, and ſubmitted themſelves to ſuch a new regiment as they beſt liked: for confirmation of which practiſes, there wanted not politike Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, (what wine is ſo ſoure that ſome hedgegraps will not yeeld) to inveſt the people and Nobles with the power over Kings, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſe of their Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marſilius Patavinus</hi> ſaith, the depoſition of a King,<note place="margin">Marſilius Patav. <hi>de tranſlat. Imporii,</hi> c. 6.</note> and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of another in his place, belongeth not to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> to any Prieſt, or to the Colledge of Prieſts, but to the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall multitude of the Subjects. So far he.</p>
            <p>From theſe, the <hi>Puritans</hi> have learned their error, of the <hi>power of States-men over Kings,</hi> then which, no opinion can be more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous: where the Nobility are as ready to practiſe, as the <hi>Puritan</hi> preachers are to preſcribe. What preſumption is it in men, to paſſe the bounds which God hath ſet them, to controll the wiſdome of the Lord, and his unſpeakable goodneſſe, when he maketh tryall of the patience of his Saints, by the out rage and tyranny of cruell Kings, that they which are found patient in trouble, conſtant in truth and loyall in ſubjection, may be crowned with glory. Were we perſwaded, that the <hi>hearts of Kings are in Gods hand,</hi> that the haires of our head are numbred, and that no affliction can befall us, which God doth not diſpoſe to the exerciſe of our Faith, the tryall of our conſtancy, or the puniſhment of our ſin, we would as well admire the Iuſtice of God, in permitting Tyrants, that our ſins may be judged, and puniſhed in this world, as praiſe his mercy and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, in giving reſt to his ſervants, under the protection of godly and gracious Princes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>The ninth Chapter ſheweth the generall conſent of the Modern Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans touching the coercion, depoſition, and killing of Kings, whom they call Tyrants.</head>
            <p>THe Citizens of <hi>Geneva,</hi> changed the Government from a <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy</hi> to a <hi>Democrity,</hi> in the year of <hi>Chriſt</hi> 1536 In the which yeare, <hi>John Calvin</hi> came into that City, to viſit his friend <hi>Farellus;</hi> And was choſen the publike reader of Divinity. At his firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming thither, he publiſhed his <hi>Teologicall Inſtitutions;</hi> Wherein he doth very learnedly and Chriſtianly intreat of the authority of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:104600:18"/>Princes, and the duty of Subjects. One only place is harſh, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous: delivered in obſcure and doubtfull tearmes, to excuſe (as I conceive) the outrage of the Citizens againſt their ſoveraigne Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates.<note place="margin">Inſtit. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 20. § 31.</note> His words are theſe, <hi>Si qui ſunt populares Magiſtratus, ad moderandam regum libidinem conſtituti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtopher Goodman</hi> publiſhed a Treatiſe of obedience at <hi>Geneva,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 119.</note> not without the very good liking and approbation of the beſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in that City, 1557, Wherein he affirmeth, That if Magiſtrates tranſgreſſe Gods Law themſelves, and command others to do the like, they loſe that honor, and obedience which otherwiſe is due un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them: and ought no more to be taken for Magiſtrates: but to be examined and puniſhed as private tranſgreſtors. So far <hi>Goodma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1577,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 206.</note> Came forth the <hi>Vindiciae contra Tyrannos,</hi> with this reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That Princes are choſen by God, eſtabliſhed by the people; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very privat man is ſubject to the Prince; the Multitude and the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of State which repreſent the Multitude, are Superiors to the Prince, yea they may judge his actions, and if he make reſiſtance, puniſh him by forcible meanes, So far he.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1588, <hi>Hermanus Renecherus</hi> publiſhed obſervations upon the 1 <hi>Pſalm,</hi> wherin he inveſteth the <hi>Presbitery</hi> with all the <hi>Popes</hi> prerogatives. Concerning the <hi>Presbiterian power</hi> over Kings, this is his notable annotation:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 72.</note> God (ſaith he) hath ordained the Civill Magiſtrate for the good of the Eccleſiaſticall order, therefore the Eccleſiaſticall State is the higheſt throne of Gods earthly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the ſupreame Seate of all excellency, and the chiefeſt Court wherein God himſelfe is preſident, to diſtribute eternall gifts to his ſervants. Whereas the politicall Empire is but as it were an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior bench, wherein Iuſtice is adminiſtred according to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the Eccleſiaſticall ſoveraignty. Thus far <hi>Renecherus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will make an end with <hi>William Bucanus,</hi> whoſe book was pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed at the requeſt and with the approbation of <hi>Beza</hi> and <hi>Gou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lartius,</hi> maine pillars of the Church of <hi>Geneva,</hi> 1602. They (ſaith <hi>Bucanus</hi>) which have any part of Office is the publike adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Common-wealth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Loco</hi> 76 p. 844.</note> as the Overſeers, Senators, Conſuls, Peeres, or Tribunes, may reſtraine the inſolency of vill Kings. Thus far he.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Puritan dangerous error,</hi> is directly repugnant to the Law, the Goſpell, the precepts of the Apoſtles, the practiſe of Martyrs, and the doctrine of the Fathers, Councels, and other Claſicall Writers, as I have proved in the 6 former Chapters, wherin the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Texts of Scripture, which the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Puritans</hi> do damnably
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:104600:18"/>abuſe againſt the Eccleſiaſtical and Civil authority of Kings, ſhal be anſwered by the godly Proteſtanes: whoſe labour God uſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme his Church ſince the yeare of our Lord, 1517. and by the ancient Fathers and Orthodoxall Writers in every age of the Church.</p>
            <p>Inferiour Magiſtrates (ſaith <hi>Iohannes Baptiſta Ficklerus</hi>) are the defenders and protectours of the Lawes and Rights of the State,<note place="margin">De jury magiſt. fol. 18.</note> and have authority (if need require) to correct and puniſh the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame King. So far <hi>Ficklerus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Engliſh fugitive, which was the Author of the booke <hi>de ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta abdicatione Henrici Tertij,</hi> affirmeth, That all the Majeſty of the Kingdome, is in the aſſembly of Stateſmen, to whom it belongeth to make Covenants with God, to diſpoſe of the aſſſiſes of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to appoint matters pertaining to war and peace,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>lib.</hi> 3 <hi>c.</hi> 8.</note> to bridle the Kingly power, and ſettle all things that belong to publike Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. So far he.</p>
            <p>And the moſt ſeditious <hi>Dolemon</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Part 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4. pag. 72.</note> that all humane Law and order Naturall, Nationall, and Poſitive, doth teach, that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, which gave Kings their authority for the common good, may reſtraine or take the ſame from them if they abuſe it to the common ill: ſo far <hi>Doleman:</hi> and of this opinion are many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as may appeare by D. <hi>Morton</hi> by whom they are diſcovered and refuted.</p>
            <p>How far this gangrene will extend, I know not. The Kings of Chriſtendome are dayly crucified, (as Chriſt their Lord was) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two theeves; I meane the <hi>Papist</hi> and <hi>Puritan,</hi> which have prepared this deadly poyſon for Princes, whom they in their own irreligious and traiterous hearts, ſhall condemne for tyranny. I hope neither Peeres nor People will be ſo fond to beleeve them, or wicked to follow them, which pretend the Reformation of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and defend he ſubverſion of Chriſtian States. If inferiour officers, or the publike aſſembly of all States, will claime this pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, it ſtandeth them upon, (as they will avoyd everlaſting damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) not to derive a title from <hi>Rome, Lacedemon,</hi> or <hi>Athens,</hi> (as <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> doth, whom the reſt follow) but from the hill of <hi>Sion,</hi> and to plead their intereſt from the Law or the Goſpell. <hi>Si mandatum non eſt praeſumptio, &amp; ad poenam proficiet, non ad praemium:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt</hi> in queſt mixt.</note> 
               <hi>quia ad contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meliam pertinet conditoris, ut contempto Domino colantur ſervi, &amp; ſpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Imperatore, adorentur Comites.</hi> If their oppoſition againſt Kings be not commanded of God, it is preſumption againſt God: for it is a contumely againſt God the Creator of all States, to deſpiſe Lords
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:104600:19"/>and honour ſervants, to contemne the Soveraigne Emperour, and to reverence the Peeres of the Empire. So far <hi>Auguſtine. My ſonne</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) <hi>feare God and the King,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 24.21.</note> 
               <hi>and meddle not with the ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: for their deſtruction ſhall come ſodainly, and who knoweth the end of them?</hi> The concluſion of all is, That Kings have ſupreame and abſolute authority under God on Earth, not becauſe all things are ſubject to their pleaſure, which were plaine tyranny, not Chriſtian Soveraignty: but becauſe all perſons, Within their Dominions, ſtand bound in Law, allegiance, and conſcience, to obey their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or to abide their puniſhment. And Kings themſelves, are no way ſubject to the controule cenſure, or puniſhment of any earthly man, but reſerved by ſpeciall prerogative to the moſt fearfull and righteous judgement of God, with whom there is no reſpect of perſons. He whoſe ſervants they are, <hi>will beat them with a rod of iron, and breake them in peeces like a potters veſſell,</hi> if they abuſe that great, and ſoueraigne power, (which God hath endued them withall,) to ſupport error, to ſuppreſſe truth, and to oppreſſe the innocent. God, of his great mercy grant us the ſpirit of truth, to direct us in all loyalty, that we being not ſeduced by theſe ſeditious Sectaries, may grow in grace, ſtand faſt in obedience, embrace love, follow peace and encreaſe more and more in the knowledge of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. To whom be all praiſe, power, and dominion now and for ever. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
